[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host gavin henry and today my
guest is roland samaj
roland savage is an entrepreneur and
corporate development professional
who has spent most of his career working
with startups in one way or another
he has taken two startups from concept
through to commercial deployment
as a leader in the corp dev team
atlassian roland successfully executed a
number of deals and was notably part of
the team that acquired trello
roland welcome to software engineering
radio hey gavin how you doing
good thanks is there anything i missed
in your bio that you'd like to add
no that's that's pretty much the
highlights excellent
i'd like to start with an overview of
what a business is
why someone creates a business and why
another person or company
acquires a business what is a business
and the types
of business in relation to software
engineering that you've come across
so ultimately a business is
an individual or a team who have gotten
together to solve a particular problem
we'll have done that with some varying
degree of success from the astonishingly
successful
to the much less so as i'm going to test
with some of my own startup experiences
and whenever another business a larger
business a more established business
seeks to acquire a startup it's
typically for one of three reasons
they're interested in the team as in the
experience and the
the knowledge and that the group has or
has accumulated
they're interested in the product what
it is they've built and
what it does its capabilities or they're
interested in their customers
they want to get access to those
customers either to make them their
customers
or to maybe sell their products to those
and in an ideal situation for the m a
professionals the corporate
professionals
it would be all three and these
businesses
are they different throughout the world
or is it more or less the same in
relation to software engineering when it
comes to software it seems same but
different
so a lot of similarities but in the us
every state has its own nuances and
across europe
some countries just have a lot more
regulations and red tape to deal with
than others
so it depends on the country you're in
yeah yes but in general
the standard structure has evolved from
all the way back
i think the origins are in throughout
martin street in london
and that has become a standard limited
liability
corporation type structure that people
use and you touched upon
a person starts a business to meet a
particular need
yeah if they don't it tends to be
short-lived you know people that are
exploring or trying to figure out what
they do after they start the business
normally find that's a challenge the
world we live in today
the most effective way to start a
business is to start with a problem
and once you've come up with a solution
to that problem more importantly you
find customers that are happy to pay you
for that solution
then you know you're onto something
something that could be its own its own
entity
so that's a very similar problem space
based on some of our other shows we've
done and just
in software engineering in general where
you don't just
create a product to find customers and
you don't just create a business to find
customers you should start with the
problem space
yeah i mean the thing is you can create
a product to find customers but the
chances are you won't be successful
and i know that sounds harsh but as you
mentioned in my bio i've had
some experience in the venture capital
world and the success rate for startups
i think is one in 20.
that's what the the statistics were the
last times i checked them
so the whole in the last five to ten
years
we've just become a lot more efficient
at starting companies and having them
become
successful and that's part of the lean
startup methodology
and some of the other you know aspects
we go about actually building these
products
but the key thing is entrepreneurs will
tell you this because
we've all experienced it you've got to
find a real pinpoint
not just something that would be a nice
to have
yeah we've done two fantastic shows
episode
448 with ma on starting your own
software company that goes into all
those things you've just touched upon
and episode 73 with joel on startups
growth and valuation which is highly
recommended
now we've covered the reasons to start a
business and
the reasons not to start business why
does a person or
another business buy another business if
that makes sense
yeah the quick answer is for
acceleration
so it's a funny thing on the in the
corporate side
when you're in the corporate development
team anytime you look at a startup so
a team of people that have developed
some product or capability
and you go talk to your engineering
folks they will always have the same
reaction
and that is that we could build this
ourselves so every company typically
thinks their engineers are the best
and some of them are but the issue at
hand
is both the time it would take to do
that so an allocation of resources
prioritization and then having the time
to actually build the thing
and also an appreciation for the effort
that's involved to make a product
successful
so whenever slack built a messaging
system
it's not just a case of figuring out the
technical challenge of being able to
send a short form text message from one
user to another
it was all the customer interviews they
did all the effort they put in the
design
and all the problems they accomplished
getting that product to market
and solved and those small things
and i think all the software engineers
appreciate they just take a
huge amount of time yeah and it's also
what to say no to as well isn't it
yeah exactly and there's a lot of the
way i think of corporate development
from the corporate side
is it's externalized r d so if you
wanted to to kick off all these programs
internally
you would have to kick off 10 for every
one successful
program so as a result whenever you look
at if you want to acquire a particular
startup
you're typically looking at the ones
that have been successful
so you're kind of happy to pay a premium
because
they've already circumnavigated the risk
associated with
whatever that particular problem and
coming up with that solution was
yeah i think in one of our other shows
i'll put in the show notes when we
chatted to one of the top guys at base
camp they have the idea where they do
internal pitches so i guess that's
similar to the corp dev
situation where they might have to pitch
10 projects
but they could just go out and buy a
company that's successful already
yeah and having it available today or
more or less today you know obviously
there's a period of time associated with
doing the deal and integrating the
company
but that's a huge deal especially as the
companies are acquiring it larger
so if you want to build that thing it
might take you 24 months
or you could do a deal and six months
from now that
capability is functional within your
product and um
why would a person want to sell a
business if they're
you know if we'd keep the terms
acquisition and selling just separate
for this question
does a startup always want to be bought
or do they want to carry on or
in your experience what have you seen
for the reasons to sell a business
yeah not always so there are some people
that want to do their own thing
be the captain of their own ship and
they may have designs to become the next
unicorn
or kick something all the way through
from inception to ipo
can a unicorn is the 1 billion dollars
yeah yeah and that's great and then
there's other companies that are
successful enough to have free access to
venture capital or other financing in
which case they don't need to be
inquired
but need an inverted commas there so
they are able to continue executing on
their plan
without any external interference and
again that's great
now there are a couple of other
categories of people who there's people
who might want to be acquired
so the most obvious answer might be
because of liquidity
so if you start a business you tend to
entrepreneurs tend to invest enough a
lot of time and money in doing that
and it might be a long time before you
were able to see any kind of return on
that
so if someone's able to come along and
tell you hey you can keep doing the job
you're doing
but we will give you a pretty decent sum
of cash there's a lot of people who find
that attractive
there are people that need to sell their
business so they have raised a certain
amount of money
that money is it will give them a
certain timeline to execute on
and if they don't have additional
financing lined up they know
if we don't find an exit point before
that money runs out then we're in a lot
of trouble
and the final reason people might want
to do it is because
as you are growing a company you're as a
founder your role will change
so if you really enjoy building products
for example and you are the cto or the
the lead product officer of a company
as that company goes you're gonna spend
a lot less time
building product a lot more time hiring
people and managing people and
allocating work
so there is an opportunity for some
teams
as they grow if they're required they
can effectively focus on the things that
they love doing
and the building the product maybe
talking to customers maybe
selling the product and figuring out
ways to market it and let the larger
company deal with the more you know
putting a very common again boring
aspects of running a company
and that's the legal financial the
chasing up customers
and dealing with all those things that
funders inevitably have to deal with
after they get to a certain
size so an acquisition is a way
sometimes
to sort of lock in what you've done
and then sort of let the larger company
help you scale it
and the scaling part can be quite
difficult as well
yeah i understand a lot of those points
because they bring home some are the
business people i know
but it sounds quite a personal decision
of why you're selling that business
yeah it always is and i should actually
add one more
a lot of people start a business with a
goal in mind
and the best way to get that goal might
be through acquisition
so if you have a product a typical
situation startups can find themselves
in
where they have a good product but they
don't have the customers people aren't
seeing it using it
then if you join forces with a larger
company that has users
then that might be the easiest way to
get your product into the hands of as
many people as possible
and for a lot of people that that kind
of is their objective that they can
make the world a better place by having
as many folks as possible use their
particular tool
to help make things more efficient or
better so it's not just about
making money it's whatever their
strategic wishes are
no and as you said it's a very personal
matter for all founders
and quite frankly after a certain point
the money matters a lot less to people
than
satisfying their initial objectives and
how long
does this process normally take if you
if we focus it down to a big company
buying a startup
do you mean the acquisition process
itself yeah let's go from
you've approached someone or you've been
approached and you've got
some money whether that's the all of
your money or some of your money
how long does that normally take so
there's normally some some form of
dating period
where the companies get to know each
other through some some mechanism
and that can be a variable amount of
time it can be very it can be a long
slow process or it can be something that
happens quite quickly
but the deal normally officially starts
whenever a term sheet or an loi
is issued and that is where the the
headline terms are agreed between both
the company and
and the startup to be acquired that's a
letter of intent
is that letter of intent yes that
basically says
this is what we want to do and how much
we're going to pay it's basically saying
hey i really do want to buy you
which is it's good to hear that in
explicit terms
we would like to pay this amount of
money we would like to pay that amount
of money over these certain terms
most commonly you know we'll do it over
a period of time
and we have these expectations you might
come and work at our headquarters or you
might continue to run the business for
12 months or
you might start working for someone
within our organization
and that kicks off the mini sort of
round of negotiations
where both sides have to agree that this
deal is what they want
and the general shape and form is
something that's acceptable to both
parties
in my book i've likened that to an
engagement proposal to get married
so it's non-binding but it's not
something that should be taken lightly
but both parties should be committed to
making it work if it's accepted and it's
a bit more than a
prenuptial isn't it it's a bit more than
that yeah yeah so
from that point to actually receiving
funds at the end of the deal
it can be done in 45 days i'd say 90
days is probably a more realistic time
frame to
wrap your head along it depends a lot on
the size of the company it depends a lot
on the complexity of the company it
depends a lot
on how familiar both sides are with each
other
so for example if you've integrated with
the company if you're
on regular speaking terms with engineers
or and product managers at the acquiring
company
if this is a conversation that's been
had before and floated
that might be a very quick process if
you're a simple company with
offices in one area everyone signed all
their agreements your customer
agreements are
are quite straightforward then the
process can go very quickly
but especially in today's world even
small companies can get very complex so
you can have employees in multiple
countries
you can have customers in multiple
countries under different agreements
and all of these are things that the
acquiring company needs to understand
and needs to figure out a plan of how to
integrate
that into their their overall offering
and how things will look
once the deal is completed excellent i'm
going to move us on to
the next section just to summarize your
last answer
it just depends on what that product is
how they do how long they've been in
business what countries
it does but i would put that 90-day
figure so even very large deals can be
completed
maybe it's longer than that maybe it's
four months rather than three months but
they don't go on for years
once the loi has been agreed it's
uncommon that everyone to move quickly
at that point
and ironically doing a small deal can
sometimes be more time consuming than
doing a larger deal
thank you so you touched upon this in
the
in the first section types of
acquisitions
now that we've covered the basics i'd
like to explore the main types of
acquisition
in your book you list three types can
you tell me what these three types are
yeah so the three main reasons a company
might want to buy a startup
is to acquire either the team the
technology
or their customers or ideally all three
so if a company is acquiring the team
that's in the valley here is known as an
aqua hire
if they're only acquiring the team and
the reason why a company might want to
do that is because the team has some set
of special skills
so you will see that happen for example
if you have a team of stanford
phd's that are working on an ai
algorithm
and the larger company wants to create
for one of a better term an ai
department
the easy thing they could do is acquire
that team and then put them to work
to solve the problem they have in mind
and how would they get to know each
other the
artificial intelligence team is they
just in the same circles
that's the role of corporate development
so corporate developments
will be scanning the ecosystems that the
company's active in
and reaching out to companies and
developing relationships so just like
business development and sales yeah much
like that
the other way it happens is in bond so
for example that small company might
have an integration
might have a marketplace app or might
otherwise be engaged with developers
and perhaps through meetups or through
some common program
in which case they get on the company's
radar internally
it's recognized then that would be
valuable to spend time getting to know
them
so that's an aqua higher in the yes the
valley
californian that's right and those are
at varying degrees of attractiveness
depending on
how available developers are at that
point in time
okay so and the second type would be
yeah for the product
so the team has built some capability
and solve some problem
that is interesting to the company so an
example of that while i was at atlassian
we bought a
video conferencing technology to
integrate with hipchat
which was a competitor to slack so
that's a very clear-cut case of
we need to find someone that has built a
video conferencing platform
that is reliable that has an
architecture that would fit with our
architecture
and is amenable to the idea of joining a
larger company
and integrating that platform with the
messaging system
so in that case you're looking for for
someone that has a very
clear set of technical requirements and
that's something driven by the
acquiring company by the acquiring
company and specifically the technical
or product team within that company
so they will have a mind and that is
something perhaps we could build
ourselves
or we could buy if something's already
out there and and in this case i mean i
think of the the amount of effort
involved with building a good and stable
platform like that you know it's
probably tens of years
worth of effort so it's a nice pick to
be able to plug that in
it's some in-depth knowledge needed for
video codex and all that yes
and the third type again then for
customers the company's interested in
the customers
so in each of those through previous
times so i mean they're obviously all
related so if you're interested in the
product then the team that's built that
product
is obviously of interest too now when
acquiring for the product
the company may or may not be interested
in
the customers that the team has captured
through that product so the company
might see the acquisition as a new line
of business
they might see the acquisition of a way
to get into an adjacent line of business
or they might see the acquisition as a
way to cross-sell their products to the
startups customers so in all instances
acquiring for access to the customers
is going to be more valuable probably
than just just acquiring the product
itself or just acquiring the team
but they might not care about the
customers and just want the product
they might not care yeah the larger
company might have
so many customers that whatever number
that the startup has it might be
interesting from the startup perspective
but much less so
from a large company perspective that
leads us nicely onto my next question is
do some companies
do acquisitions to kill technology or to
learn about
or gain expertise in that technology are
you not caring so much about the revenue
or products
almost all companies will care more
about the technology probably
than the customers involved they say
almost all again it depends
again if someone was to buy slack they
have whatever many
tens of millions of users that's
interesting you know that's valuable
yeah
salesforce box like not too long yeah
right exactly
but a lot of the times the company is
buying the technical capability
companies generally don't buy other
companies just to shut them down
that's an expensive way to put a
competitor out of business
i think it's illegal in certain
circumstances
but it's also just if you want to
compete with why not just compete with
them why not just beat them by
building a better product or offering a
lower price we're doing something along
those lines
now that doesn't mean the companies
aren't acquired and the product line
sunsetted
eventually we see that happen i think
microsoft acquiring wunderlist i think
that
sunset and that that's a good example
but it tends to be more of a
change of priorities or change of
direction or perhaps
the intention was made to buy a
technology with the gold the skill in it
and it just turns out after deep
investigation
that just doesn't work that was a
premise that ultimately
couldn't be proven so again it comes
down to what is of interest
to the acquiring company really yes and
one of the things
points i try to get to in my book is
it's really important for the
people on the startup side to really
understand what the
acquiring company has in mind so all of
these approaches are valid
providing people know what they're
getting into so if there's a risk
associated with shutting
a program down for example if startups
see that as their baby under no
circumstances do they want that
product to be you know end of life they
need to know that going in
and it sort of holds everyone involved
to have that conversation openly
i've got a link to your book in the show
notes but just to let the listeners know
it's called
how how to stick landing or you can tell
me what it's called
how to stick the landing the m a
handbook for startups
excellent so in your experience and what
you've
been through yourself and what you see
which type of those three types of
acquisition
are most successful in almost all
circumstances is the combination
i would say the customers
matter less for a lot of the deals that
are done
people are interested in the combination
of the team and technology
however customers validate the
technology
so if you've built something and nobody
wants to use it
it has to be a pretty well understood
niche kiosk
for someone to want to buy that it's
quite a chicken and egg isn't it
it is but you don't necessarily if
you've got 100 customers for example
that might be enough to validate the
product
yeah you've got a varied enough input
for customers to
have the right feature set and give you
some guidance yeah
so it's always nice when there's
customers but you know a lot of the time
for example these larger companies like
a sales force
might simply be looking at at your
company
as an additional feature they would add
in perhaps not even charge for
just to improve the customer experience
and the retention associated with it
and are you allowed to talk about the
reasons that atlassian bought trello
just in broad terms yeah where would
they fit in
the type well they were definitely there
was definitely a highly talented team
there
and they had a fantastic product so
i don't think it was a secret they were
monetizing their customer set and they
did have an awful lot of customers
but i think what was exciting for
atlassian was
this lightweight visual very easy to use
intuitive tool that trello had created
and what that would bring to the
atlassian offering which
at the time was jira tends to be a very
quite a heavyweight tool
command line driven more than oh the
gyro yeah
i don't know how you say it yeah the
ticket system source control
it's very very successful but it's it's
kind of it's a product built by
engineers for engineers
so you can see that there's having the
travel definitely
represents the whole new way of sort of
building products
that would seem very valuable to
atlassian and then in terms i think for
trello having access to the you know the
enormous
ecosystem of blasian customers
and their products which you know an
awful lot of people use
was one of those sort of win-win
scenarios and it was a success
yeah i think so excellent we actually
use trello to do all the
different stages of the shows at
software engineering radio yeah they're
a great bunch they've just a tremendous
team there
it's a great pleasure to work with them
that's a product i like excellent i'm
going to take us on to the
next section i'd like to discuss getting
a line for an offer
are you going out and trying to find
someone to acquire you or what happens
if you are approached out of the blue
so if you are approached so you haven't
had any intention
plan or maybe you have to be acquired is
there a particular
way to value your startup or how do you
do that
yeah i think you're asking two different
questions there so first and foremost
it's how these offers manifest
and my key piece of advice here is not
to be surprised
and by that i mean if you are a startup
you should as you're developing along
your journey have a good idea
for the type of folks that might be
interested in acquiring your business
because there you're probably your
closest neighbors or biggest competitors
they also as you're developing will
probably have a number of programs that
you might want to build yourself
up and those are the partner partnership
programs the hackathons the
even engaging with them a lot of large
companies have programs that have
outreach towards startups
it's a good way to get access to
knowledge and expertise and even advice
so it's less likely that you would be
approaching something you should be
thinking about
yeah yeah you don't have to do a deal
but you should know who might be
interested in buying you
and whenever you're talking to a startup
and they just think well it'll be google
it's like well would it think through
that and who might be blogging right now
give that example of the video
technology you should it's incumbent on
the leader of a
company like that to know who's
interested in video technology right now
who's writing blogs about wouldn't it be
great to have a
a great video technology because if not
a if not an acquisition opportunity that
might be a business development
opportunity that might be a customer
prospect
yeah it could be a partnership rather
than an acquisition yeah so it's never
clear at the start of the of the
conversation
where where it might lead and that's
true in the company side too so
the roots of having becoming a customer
becoming a partner
or becoming an acquirer they all start
the same way and that starts with
hearing about the startup getting to
know the startup and getting to
understand the startups capabilities
we'll stick with the startup that has
intention of being acquired and
they're putting themselves in the
different circles is a startup valuation
different from a valuation of a business
that is fully sufficient or has been
going a while
the principles are the same i mean
there's a risk associated if the company
requires additional financing in order
to
remain solvent and then the next
question would be how likely are they to
get that
additional financing but just to be
specific the whether the offer is
solicited or
has been worked towards evaluation is
much an art as it is a science
so things that startup founders want to
keep in mind
is look for comparable transactions so
look for companies that are in some
shape or form like yours
that have been acquired and how much and
the amounts have been
disclosed which does not always happen
probably happens
less than half the time i suspect and
the reason that's important is
it is very hard to value a business that
doesn't have a stable recurring
growing revenue stream it gets very
subjective at that point of view
and it's also worth pointing out that a
company the same company might be worth
different amounts to different
acquirers the reason being that whenever
i acquire a startup
i am going to want to let's say either
sell their product to my customers
or sell my product to their customers or
some combination of the two
and depending on what my product is the
number of customers i have
my price point i might arrive at a very
different
valuation as a different company that
has more or less customers or charges a
greater or lower
amount for their product and that's
something to keep in mind
both valuations will be correct from the
perspective of the acquirer
and i suppose it depends say a company's
running stuff in
private hybrid clouds and other ones
purely in the cloud
it depends how the acquirer does things
some of that might be useful some of it
might not be so that can change
yeah it's the maxim is that all deals
are different
but the question is how much does the
acquirer
value what you've done if they value
all the aspects about what you've built
how you've built it how you deploy it
etc
you should feel that they're offering
you're going to get an offer reflecting
the full value
at that point in time if they only want
part of it you know let's say you're
an on-prem solution and a cloud solution
and they're only interested in the cloud
solution then
that on-prem side of your business is
effectively worthless to the acquiring
company
now again there's some sense of
negotiation when it comes to determining
value
where and there's got to be an
acknowledgement that got to meet
somewhere
somewhere in the middle but it's always
worthwhile keeping that in mind they
could just see one part of that as
something that's a pain and they're
gonna have to sunset at some point and
do migrations
yes so that leads me nicely on to my
next question
where do we see the crazy numbers come
from in the press
the unicorns and they might be a team of
20 or 30 but they're just valued
way way way more than makes sense do you
have any insight as to
how that works well a question the
are they valued more than make sense are
those numbers crazy
so and by that i'm not been cute but
it's a small
numbers of people small groups of people
have created products
that have been enormously successful and
have
attracted huge numbers of customers
and potentially generated huge amounts
of revenue
so whenever you see those silly numbers
someone has sat down and think this
company will generate
revenues that would justify that
valuation
and either they are doing it or there is
a path that they will do it at some
point in the future
people doing these deals generally
aren't stupid they're not throwing money
away
they see some super valuable pathway
i've actually got an analogy there to
think about and it's whenever google
bought youtube
at the time i believe that was pillared
as i think they paid a billion dollars
at the time
i think that that deal was pillared as
being a
you're crazy for paying so much money
for youtube and that that was just a
height of
extravagance whereas what would youtube
be worth now if it was independently
valued it's something
billions of people use every day the
question is
how much is that company worth to that
particular acquirer and why
and that cleverness and insight comes
from the
team getting bought to say hold on a
minute we're potentially worth this much
to you
again i i would think very much my goal
in life is to try to break down the
barrier between the acquirer and the
acquired
i mean ultimately whenever you're
deciding to join forces
again go back to that marriage analogy
it's a marriage you have a shared goal
you're working towards
so by themselves there is a value to be
created through an acquisition
in that by themselves the smaller
company may not be able to achieve
the greatness that could be achieved
through the acquisition
whenever we build the business case for
acquisition one of the questions we
answer
is how does one plus one equal three how
by putting our two pieces of the puzzle
together
do we get something that's greater than
the sum of the parts i understand yeah
so yeah it's really again comes down to
the desires of
the people selling and the bigger
picture
yeah and ultimately that combined
offering might be closer to
realizing the vision of both companies
than they do by themselves
going back to the offer stage now that
we covered off
crazy numbers are in fact lack of
insight from the reading
of the article maybe we've touched on
the timeline in the stages
after an awful letter could you just
give us a recap on that
yeah so after the loi has been agreed
typically the stages after that will be
due diligence which is for the acquiring
company to understand
everything about what it is they're
buying will be the
agreement of the legal documentation
which is largely a stage of lawyers like
arguing with each other and working out
the fine detail
from a legal perspective of the deal
there will be a phrase of integration
which should begin before the deal
closes
but will be in effect the sequence of
steps that happen
immediately after the deal closes and
then closing itself closing is when
people put their their signatures on
paper
she accounts from a legal perspective
the two become one
and at the closing stage yes if you're
already
having chats about integration and
obviously
everything really nd aid and all that
type of stuff so you're sharing things
yes at what point up until completion
can you both just go
nah i'm not interested the common
refrain is a deal is not done till it's
done
so right up until both signatures are
exchanged
and the legal documents have been
executed one party can walk away from
the transaction
but you still just go on faith yeah so
the process is
set up to build confidence as you go
through
so for example if there's some problem
with the term sheet with the loi
then you need to have that conversation
before you go and spend six figures on
lawyers in the contents and anyone else
you might need
you do want to disrupt your business for
three months just to ultimately walk
away
so it's important to have those hard
conversations earlier
and i mentioned integration because
that's a huge deal
to understand post deal who you're going
to be reporting to
is the founder going to be reporting
directly to the ceo or is it going to be
reporting to someone four or five levels
done
does the team have to relocate or not
does everyone in the team get a job
or not will the condition yeah i've seen
your um
your helpful guide to the back of your
book sort of help you go through that
and i've seen some
deals in the press and things where and
some chats i've had with some other
guests
where integrations just either stagnate
or just don't happen
the acquired company may have been
better being
just a partner if they haven't got that
been nailed yeah well it's again this is
something that's important for both
sides to agree on
so the most important determinant for
the success of a deal
is the integration and that needs to be
thought through
and it's important because that there
are different people involved
in the doing of the deal so the folks
involved in actually doing the deal
are not the same folks that are going to
be involved with running the combined
entity we're going to touch upon
integration in the next section so so
you're moving along nicely
you've done completion do you then get a
big fat check in one go or
not check but you know what i mean how
does that work yeah so
typically once the deal closes there
will be some
transfer of funds so the way deals
normally work
i'll speak just to my experience here in
silicon valley is
typically you will you will be given
some portion of the funds at closing
and then have a retention piece that
will probably best over two to four
years
so imagine you get a fifth of the funds
upon closing then
another fifth after year one another
fifth after year two another fifth after
year three
another fifth after year four so upon
closing yes wires will be initiated but
not for the full amount
so it would be a very foolish thing for
an acquiring company to suddenly
hand different group of people a large
check and then just hope everything
works out after that
that's really not everyone's best
interest and that's also
called uh an earn out depending on the
structure yes it can be internet
yeah or a holdback is the other way it's
commonly done
and does it cost money to be acquired i
think we touched on that a little bit
yes most importantly it costs a lot of
time and effort from the founders
it will be disruptive for a period of
months while you go through the process
and that holds everything else doesn't
it yeah so you've got to be careful one
of the scariest things for me being on
corporate side
when acquiring a startup was making sure
that we didn't topple them like a small
boat
been toppled by you know the wake of a
big boat while we went through that
process
because remember there is a potential
that you would walk away after
occupying their their mind and their
head space for
a couple of months you always have to be
as cautious about that and as efficient
as possible in addition commonly you
would spend six figures on a lawyer
and work through this process as well or
something close to that
i talked about the lawyers and
accountants how much does the inquiry
company need to know
about your company everything right the
acquiring company
can't acquire you and then suddenly find
out that you've been sued
well that just can't happen they can
acquire you and find there's employee
issues
they can acquire you and find out
actually you had a founder
who kind of owns the ip or could make a
claim when owning the ip
after the deal closes and sue them for
more than the deal
is worth so that could be something like
they created the software themselves
before they start
their legal entity not just that again
i'm not up to date on uk law
but if everyone who's ever worked for
the company
hasn't signed an ip assignment to the
company
then the company itself doesn't have
full chain of custody
on the ip which means someone could buy
the company
and someone else comes out of the
woodwork and say hey i worked on that i
worked in a really important piece
and it's really hard to prove that they
didn't and they potentially could have a
legal kingdom and that's just a huge
headache nobody wants to deal with
and that's covered under the term due
diligence isn't it
all of that yes and what's our team is
typical
to have on the side of the company
getting acquired it's not the big
company the small company
typically you'll have the founders
involved with
probably someone to provide definitely
someone to provide legal advice
so a good m a lawyer and then probably
someone help on the finance side
and m a is mergers and acquisitions
mergers and acquisition yes
and then someone on the finance side so
part of the process will be
to review audited financials and make
sure
everything's understood and clear now
that might be the cfo if the company's
had it it might be one of the board
members if they're experienced
or it could be an independent financial
advisor okay just to
round off this section we're bang on
time so that's good
so yeah due diligence tell them
everything you need to know
you need a good team to support you to
make sure you're not getting into
something
on both sides that you're not privy to
and if you're allowed to say
i don't think i've asked this already
how did the atlassian one happen again
they approached cello is that correct
it's funny it's
something i was just writing about those
large deals
and the trello deal was a 425 million
dollar deal
it's pretty large yeah those are in
process for
like trello was on our radar for years
scott would make a point of
trying to meet with joel and michael
whenever he was in new york
so we tried to build a relationship over
over a period of time
and understand where they where they
were where they were going
so it's hard to come up with just one
inception point that's why when i say
it shouldn't be these acquisition offers
shouldn't come out of the blue
you should know someone's interested in
you and be helpful and facilitating
those relationships
excellent so let's say we're now we've
been bought
the press is out we're all extremely
happy
we've got to do the integration and we
may potentially head off into the sunset
once that er now or you know handover
period
is done so how do we start merging
things at all
is that decided up front before
completion or ideally at least at a high
level
it is there's actually a lot of things
that needs to happen
in reasonably short order so for example
the if you have customers
are generating revenue you've got to
join you've got to combine that with the
acquiring company
so how you go about buying our acquiring
customers
has got to be aligned with their way of
going about combined customers
and then where the cash flows the
systems they run through
and how they're ultimately reconciled
there needs to be a plan for combining
notes
ultimately moving to one standard the
various groups have to get to know each
other
so the way you build product has to
align with how the the big company
builds the product and there needs to be
a plan
of how they're going to be integrated
the specifics of that depends on
sometimes you'll find companies run more
or less independently for
six to 12 months or right away it might
be
how do we plumb our system into your
system so we can offer that joint
offering to the customers
so you've got them the financial part
the sales part the operational part
autumn to marginal line yeah the hr part
probably happens
before deal closing in that all the the
employees are given new
contracts whatever share save or
whatever share scene they were on with
the old company
they're now on a new one with the new
company so that has to happen as well
did you say share scheme there yeah yeah
equity equity yeah
and have you ever seen instances where a
company buys a product
to get products market fit and the
customers but scraps a product and
rewrites it all from scratch
that'd be pretty crazy i haven't
personally seen that
it's actually it's not that crazy
so i think it's common as products
grow and expand that they're all
rewritten
or certainly redeveloped as they go so
it is possible that
you might acquire the effectively turn
of a version 2.0 of the product
that may be perhaps written on a
different platform that's more scalable
or utilizing new languages or or
capabilities
that the startup team wasn't as familiar
with
so in general i would think of it more
of an iteration or an evolution
rather than a scrapping and in general
do things always run smoothly with
integration
in general things tend to not run
smoothly but that's that's the challenge
so there's a transition period well
actually let's start off with a nice bit
you start off with a honeymoon period
so whenever a deal happens normally
everyone's very excited about that
so there's a new shiny thing been
brought into the company and everyone's
quite excited to have that i think in
your book you discuss
being loved to death don't you yes
well if you think about it and a company
that has 100 people in it
and they've been bought by a company
that has 5000 people in it you suddenly
find every engineer wants to talk to the
very small number of engineers on the
other side
and suddenly they're spending the whole
first month fielding
coffee requests and because they don't
know who's who in the new organization
people are tend to be very polite so
they effectively can be brought to a
stand still just through people being
curious
and interested and wanting to waste them
well which is all good but like all
things there needs to be balance there
and how do they protect themselves and
those situations
ideally there should be an integration
manager on the company side
who can effectively be the bad cop to
say hey
these people already have jobs which
occupied 100
of their time before being acquired they
now have to do all the acquisition
activities which is probably another
good hundred percent of their time
and they are going to want to meet and
integrate and connect and
understand everything about the new
company so we just can't do everything
all at once so maybe let's let's
face things and let's take things
gradually and
does all the knowledge get transferred i
don't know if the knowledge
if it needs to get transferred but there
are definitely interfaces
need to happen so there's going to be
some some connection points
so at a product level or an engineering
level you definitely want a mind mail to
happen
between certainly between key resources
on both sides
but overall ideally the startup that's
been acquired should be able to bring
some new energy maybe some new processes
maybe some new practices about how they
do things
because startups can normally move
quickly iterate quickly
and the larger company in turn can help
with
okay here's the more standardized
processes we use
because for a large company with many
customers stability is key
providing customer support it's at risk
is key so if you can combine those
things
it should be quite powerful but it takes
time and it takes time for both sides to
kind of get comfortable with each other
it should be mapped out before it should
be mapped out like all things i mean you
should you should have a plan and then
you should have the ability to
stray off plan where necessary is that
usually part of
the payouts over the next few years in
an ideal world the payouts should be
time-based
everyone should be understood to be
doing their best in the situation
sometimes the payouts will be
milestone-based and
the reason why i caution and i'm
accepting that
is because the person who accepts the
milestone payment
may not be in full control of all the
effort that's required to satisfy the
milestone
i'll give you a very simple example
let's say you agree that
you have 500 000 customers and you agree
that you would get a big payment
you get to 1 million customers but in
order to do that you need to add an
extra 100 engineers
and then when recruiting comes around
you're only able to add 50 engineers
so if everyone's making best efforts
you're in a sticky situation there
you know so people are working hard to
meet their goal
but for reasons sort of not their fault
they're unable to complete that goal
it's not really done until those two to
four years
are complete is it yeah that that would
be the best situation is that
you're working to that two to four year
plan where after that time
both all the knowledge has been you know
integrated to the combined
company the two products are effectively
one product
and at that point it becomes much less
important to know
you know who came from company a or
company b they're just kind of
the one team at that point and do they
ever do milestones
payments based on your turnover of that
company
that can happen it depends on the
specific of the deals so yeah it just
depends on
what's going on and what happens if the
thing you love the most
in your startup isn't used you know you
say you've got a couple of products
but they're not interested in your baby
is that just when you have to suck up
well that should be something that could
have been perceived before the deal's
done
and if it's really important to you you
should be aware of that the thing to
remember when you've sold your company
you have sold your company
so you are seeding control to someone
else and
what can happen sometime is that
priorities simply change
and you know the world around so for
example covey just happened last year
i can guarantee road maps were rewritten
oh yeah i did hear about that
regardless of the intent the real world
comes into play
and suddenly something might be dropped
something might be reprioritized
that's just part of the process and
ideally the thing you love most
is probably the thing that makes you
most interesting to the acquirer
and that's usually how it works and you
would be working on some plan to get
that thing into as many people's hands
as possible
again there is a reality there that's
just got to be acknowledged
and that's potentially something you
could build into the terms of the
two to four years yeah potentially so
how do we confirm
or validate a successful or unsuccessful
or failure of an acquisition
i did the acquisition succeed it's
actually harder to do than you might
think
so the only way you could reasonably do
that
is if you have a stated shared goal at
the time of the acquisition
so if you have we're going to buy
product a
combine it with product b and at the end
of four years we expect to have
a million users using it or we expect to
be generating 10 million dollars for the
revenue
through that then it's very clear to say
whether it's successful or not
successful
in reality four years after an
acquisition the companies have been
reorganized several times
especially if it's high growth the teams
have been combined
the products have been combined and it's
very hard to pick apart what part was
product and what part was product b
also the benefits might be hard to
quantify
so take the example where you are buying
a small company
that turns into a feature a much larger
project product
that customers are using and it creates
more delight with those customers
well how do you attribute increased
customer happiness
or lower or higher customer attention to
that one feature
because there's a lot a lot more going
along
so it's quite hard to define the success
criteria for an acquisition
it is and over what time period again
going back to the google deal with
youtube
that did turn out to be hugely
successful but not right away
it was probably years later but how
would you know if the acquisition failed
sometimes it's obvious sometimes
there'll be a combined go-to-market
effort that just doesn't work
sometimes you acquire customers and
customers leave because they
they like working with a small company
and they don't want to be with the large
company
or they don't want to be with that
particular large company
sometimes there's a breakdown among the
with the finding team and they'll leave
sometimes that happens publicly
yeah you mentioned that in your book to
always think about the fact that you're
gonna
i'm paraphrasing but basically you
always think you're gonna come across
those people again
you know yeah as you should treat other
people in life it's not
slay everyone yeah and it's just it is a
hard process
you know and that's that's the other
thing to acknowledge i mean combining
two
these can be difficult and also the role
of a startup
startup ceo within a larger organization
can be very powerful if they know how to
leverage you or can just not be
you could then be someone that is just
making waves within a
much more structured environment and
that might be you know
difficult there has to be some evolution
of role there
can you anticipate these types of
failures you probably get a few signs up
front
sometimes i mean it's the good fences
make for good neighbors i mean as much
as possible
you want to have discussions on
alignment
um and especially roles before the deal
closes so
transparency is key here it was a gift
at atlassian
one of their values is open company and
that allowed us to be clear
here's how things are going to be and
those conversations aren't always easy
and on both sides but it's best that
they're had
and they're not sort of eventually
evolved into
when it's not clear who's going to
report to who or when it's not clear
what
what that combined offering is going to
be or who's going to drive
that's where the frictions can tend to
tend to bubble up the surface
and have you seen situations where it
didn't fail
but there might have been some
overpayment in terms of the actual value
that they got again it's hard to
quantify that
what i will say is i've seen a situation
where
the full value hadn't been realized in
the time
along the original timeline and it was
just that additional additional
priorities got in the way
but then eventually that move was taken
and it seemed to be quite successful
i guess potentially a lot of companies
that acquired and completion just
happened before march last year
you know couldn't have predicted 12
months covered so
these things i happen it was for you and
i 2008 wasn't that long ago
there are corrections in the market and
not just that there's new competitors
you know there's new people there's
there's new approaches
so it's you're kind of hitting a moving
object with a moving object
and to get to a new destination but
that's part of it
if someone has acquired your business
for a reason especially if it's
significant the chances are that that is
something that's important to them
they want to follow through so measuring
business value and
getting the most out of the acquisition
should be a given at the start but
things change over the two to four years
things change over time yeah
and are there companies out there that
look at acquisitions
and treat them like a portfolio where
they care about the overall return but
expect some to fail kind of like
private equity and investors and things
yeah
that's particularly the model of private
equity investors and
what they're typically trying to do is
find an asset company
and then apply whatever their system is
to enable that asset more so part of
that system might be for example that
they have industry connections or they
have back office support
or they have scaling through the next
stage of the company
and typically they will invest in a lot
or buy a lot of companies and kind of
run them pretty hard to see the return
they're after and that would be your
sort of classic round a round b c type
funding where they're getting money
but not actually relinquishing all of
the ownership of the company
no no so i would treat venture capital
investment or
the intent is very much to invest in the
team that's operating the company
and help them get to the next stage
whereas a private equity investment
tends to be more
tends to be larger typically and also
tends to be more to alter of course
somehow
or adjust course or accelerate the
course through some
specific mechanism that's your pe and
your vc hasn't
the line blurs between some of them
these days but you'll kind of know it
when you see it
excellent i think that's been a a great
summary of the timelines and i'd like to
start wrapping up the show now that's
okay ron
knowing what is involved in being
acquired it's extremely important for
software engineers and companies
but if there's one thing a budding
entrepreneur should remember from our
show what would you like that to be
just to be mindful about the process
it's good to understand the process
and knowledge is par so if you know
what's going to happen
you're better prepared to deal with it
and and have the conversations you
really need to have
and um again a copy of your book would
be the best starting place
yeah that's that's probably a good start
important yeah and is there anything
key or anything at all that i missed
that you'd like to mention
not really the one thing i would talk
about is this
this need for transparency in the
process
that's a two-way street so i think it
beholds the acquiring companies to be
transparent about their intentions
because you can short-circuit some
conversations very quickly
but also for the startups being acquired
to be as open as you possibly can
it's very hard to have conversation and
i've had it where someone said
you should buy us and say well how many
customers have you got and say i'm not
telling you
says well how does your product work i'm
not telling you that either and it's
like how do you expect me to buy you you
know i just
hope that what you're saying is true
it's like that really doesn't make any
sense
yeah i suppose that's kind of like the
car analogy i want to buy that car but
you're not allowed to see it or you're
not allowed to test drive it
so how can i really understand and as i
said the
processes about how we develop software
are changing
so it's got like most people are
blogging their customer numbers you know
or been very open about their monster
raising and
their headcounts and things like that so
a lot of the times this isn't sensitive
information it's stuff that can be
readily shared and might help the
company get to a decision
but some of it is press police though so
you have to dig into it
yeah i've got a minute or so left i've
got a question about atlassian and
trello
what was the most difficult part if
you're allowed to
say or what could have been prepared for
better during the whole process
no i i think if i was to to say from
outsider probably the most difficult
part was convincing them to
to sell the business because they were
kind of doing so well by themselves so
there's a truism and acquisitions that
the company you want to acquire
don't want to sell themselves because
they're doing so well that's a very good
point you
know why would you and the companies
that want you to buy them you probably
don't want to buy them
because they want to sell because
they're not seeing that you know the
growth
yeah they might pick up themselves quite
a lot yeah so so the key is really is is
trying to identify a shared goal
and how both sides can kind of
contribute towards that goal
which kind of goes back to the point of
finding the pain point to solve in your
business or your product
yeah ultimately yes perfect so where can
people find out more
if they want to reach out you've got
your twitter account how else can people
get in touch
yeah linkedin look for roland savage or
visit my website at corkdev dot io
and you've got a medium.com presence i
do have a medium website and i have a
series now on adding transparency to the
m a process and that is just roll on
savage on medium
roland thank you for coming on the show
it's been a real pleasure this is gavin
henry for software engineering radio
thank you for listening thanks for
having me
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening